Hello, we start the penultimate perek ראשית הגז reishis hageiz. *Reishit HaGez*,
קלה עמוד א *Kuf Lamed Heh Amud Aleph*, top of the page.
And so we've got the first gift of the כהנים *Kohanim* from
non-korbanot, the זרוע לחיים וקיבה zeroa lechayayim vekeiva. *Zroa Lechayayim veKeivah*, the
meat of the various parts. And now we deal with the shearings
which is limited to the sheep. So let's take a look, that's
the first point that the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* makes. ראשית הגז reishis
hageiz. *Reishit HaGez*, the first of the shearings, נוהג בארץ ובחוצה לארץ
*noheg ba-Aretz u-ve-chutz la-Aretz*, applies in ארץ ישראל Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* and
outside of ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, בפני הבית ושלא בפני הבית *bifnei
ha-bayit ve-lo bifnei ha-bayit*, whether there's a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit
HaMikdash* or not, which is pretty obvious since it has nothing to
do with ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, בחולין אבל לא במוקדשין *be-chulin aval
lo be-mukdashin*, only in non-sanctified animals, not in sanctified animals, like we
were taught by זרוע לחיים וקיבה zero'a lechayayim ve-keivah, *Zroa Lechayayim veKeivah*.
Interestingly, here we do not have a whole digression of or about
the whether they were sanctified before or after the blemish. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* will even skip that over last time. Right, that we
will, don't worry, we'll get to that when we get to בכורות
*Bechorot*. חומר בזרוע ובלחיים ובקיבה מראשית הגז mereishis hagez, *Chomer ba-zroa u-ve-lechayayim
u-va-keivah mi-reishit ha-gez*. There are stringencies, meaning greater scope of זרוע zroa
לחיים lechayayim וקיבה vekeyva, *Zroa Lechayayim veKeivah* than from the first shearings.
שהזרוע והלחיים והקיבה *She-ha-zroa ve-ha-lechayayim ve-ha-keivah*, the arm, the jaw, and the
stomach, the meat gifts from the slaughtering from slaughtered animals, נוהגים בבקר
ובצאן *nohagim ba-bakar u-va-tzon*, they apply whether to cattle or to sheep,
במרובה ובמועט *be-merubeh u-ve-muat*, whether you're doing many cattle and sheep or
maybe only one, just one sheep, one cow, you give these gifts.
בראשית bereshit הגז hagaz. *U-ve-reishit ha-gez*, the first shearings, אינו נוהג אלא
Ella ברחלות *eino noheg ela bi-rachelot*, is only by lambs, right, no
shearings by goats or by cows, even though they would use goat
hair, that was not considered גז geiz, *gez*.
Even in the מקדש *Mikdash*, right, it's
not saying they wouldn't use that, but it was not under the
word shearing. Okay, so shearing only applies to sheep. ואינו נוהג אלא
ela במרובה
*Ve-eino noheg ela be-merubeh*, and only with many. Now that's not so
clear from the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*, but the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* says
ראשית reishis גז gez צאנך tzoncha, *reishit gez tzoncha*. So צאן *tzon*,
right, is not like a lamb. צאן *tzon* is a sense of
like when you, for example, if you were to say the word
cattle, you would not think you're talking about one cow. You're talking
about a group of cattle, right? So צאן *tzon* seems to have
similar implications, it doesn't mean one, you would never say one sheep
is a צאן *tzon*. צאן *tzon* is a like, what? A
flock. A flock, thank you, that was the word. Flock. So flock.
So what's a flock? So it's not just one. Right. So how
much? וכמה הוא מרובה *Ve-chama hu merubeh*? And how much is a
flock? What's the minimum for a flock? בית Beit שמאי אומרים שתי
רחלות *Beit Shammai omrim shtei rachelot*, two,
the bare minimum. Again, בית Beit שמאי *Beit Shammai* here is more
stringent because how much is a flock?
Right, exactly.
Because, well, if you're a very poor person, that's the smallest possible
flock. But again, that's more stringent, even two is enough to obligate
you. שנאמר יחיה איש עגלת בקר ושתי צאן *shene'emar yichyeh ish egla
bakar u-shtei tzon*,
a person will sustain a calf and
two flock. So he says, you see it's called flock even with
two. ובית הלל אומרים חמש *U-Veit Hillel omrim chamesh*, no, five. שנאמר
חמש צאן עשויות *shene'emar chamesh tzon asuyot*, five of the flock or
five sheep, you know, here it's funny because here it uses the
word צאן *tzon*, which means flock, but you also have the thing
by בקר *bakar*, cattle, right? It says שתי בקר *shtei bakar*, so
two of the flock or two, so it sometimes when it comes
with a number it can actually mean the members of the flock
or the members of the cattle. Anyway, here it says five of
the flock that are laden with their, you know, with their wool.
So shearing applies. Right, exactly, exactly. You know, how does each one
deal with the other פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*? Here at least according to
בית Beit הלל *Beit Hillel* you do have the sense of עשויות
*asuyot*, you know, laden with their wool, so it is more of
the context. רבי Rabbi דוסא בן הרכינס אומר חמש רחלות גזוזות מנה
מנה ופרס חייבות בראשית הגז *Rabbi Dosa ben Harkinas omer chamesh rachelot
guzot mane mane u-pras chayavot be-reishit ha-gez*. That
there either needs to actually be each of the sheep have to
produce a minimum amount of wool to be considered
a real shearing. If you know, a sheep only got some like,
you know, a tiny bit of wool then it wasn't really a
shearing of the sheep. So yes, five, but how much has to
come from each sheep? So one and a half מנה *mane*, פרס
*pras* is a half. So we'll discuss later exactly how much that
weighs and so on, that will come not today, but for now
we'll just understand that that is a certain size of significance, not
tiny but not huge. That means that less than that for him
would not be considered a real shearing.
Do you give all that to the כהן kohen. *kohen* or?
No, that's how much you need to shear off of each sheep
to be obligated. Then we'll talk about once you've sheared all of
that, how much do you give to the כהן kohen. *kohen*? That's
coming up in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. וחכמים אומרים חמש רחלות גזוזות
כל שהוא *Ve-Chachamim omrim chamesh rachelot guzot kol shehu*.
No, it's five sheep even if you only get the tiniest amount
off of each sheep. There is not a minimum amount that each
sheep has to produce. Of course, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going
to ask how much is a כל שהוא *kol shehu*. Okay. וכמה
נותן לו lo, *Ve-chama noten lo*?
And how much do you give the כהן kohen *kohen* now that
we know how much you need to be obligated? How much do
you give the כהן kohen *kohen*? וכמה נותן לו lo משקל חמש
סלעים ביהודה שהן עשר סלעים בגליל *Ve-chama noten lo mishkal chamesh sela'im
bi-Yehuda shehen eser sela'im ba-Galil*. So
something that weighs five סלע *sela* in Judea, which weighs ten סלע
*sela* in Galilee. So obviously the Judean סלעים *sela'im* were twice as
big or twice as heavy as the Galilean. ones and a סלע
*sela* was like a coin. So again, when I do not come
with that information today, we're not going to do it in the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* today, but when we get to it in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, I will come with like weights and proportions so
we can, you know, translate that into our terms, but anyway a
certain amount, you know, of like a essentially I'm guessing it's around
a handful of wool is the minimum that you give. Now the
other question is, is it proportional to how much you shear or
even if you shear a thousand sheep, is that all you have
to give, right? Or is that the minimum but if you have
a lot of shearing then you would give a higher proportion, which
is actually what we will see in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. So
that's a question both of the minimum but also is there a
proportional amount as well? Okay, so the bare minimum, the bare minimum
is the weight of these, no, but we'll see in the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara*, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* talks about a proportion. The bare
minimum is a weight, is an amount that weighs this amount, these
five coins or ten coins. מלובן *Meluban*, if it has to be
clean, ולא צואי *velo tzoi*, and not dirty. Okay, so when you
originally shear it, you know, I mean the wool has been out
in the environment, the sheep's been in mud or whatever, so you've
got to clean it, you don't want to give them it, you
know, in its pre-processed
state, in its dirty state.
You still shear from the black sheep of the family, right?
Well, that's true, yeah.
But you don't clean the sheep before you shear, you're saying it's
after. Right, yeah, sure.
Doesn't
work
for- I
mean, maybe it might work to have them walk through a lake
or something or water them down before shearing, I don't know if
it makes it easier or harder. I know for me it's easier
for me to shave after I've taken a shower, I don't know
about sheep. But anyway, but even if you did that, I still
assume, you know, whatever, you to do a real job of cleaning,
obviously you take the wool and I assume, you know, you serious
water and soap and whatever, but it's
more of a combing.
Combing because it has lanolin.
I'm sure combing is also part of it, but doesn't- isn't there
also like a cleaning in terms of dirt? I mean, I assume
that there's both. All right, we'll have to check Wikipedia about how
they actually- I see people are already doing that.
Okay, we will- sheep have lanolin.
Okay, what's lanolin?
Lanolin is an oil in the actual garment of the- what do
you call it? The wool. So it's not as simple as...
Okay, okay, we'll- I'm sure we'll find out in a minute what
exactly how it's done. Okay. Now
שנאמר *Shene'emar*, now כדי לעשות ממנו בגד קטן *kedei la'asot mimenu beged
katan*, in order that he could make a small garment. Yeah, basically
like a little belt, let's say a tiny little, you know, a
tiny little belt. שנאמר *Shene'emar*, as it says, תתן titein לו lo.
*titen lo*, שיהא בו כדי מתנה *sheyehe bo kedei matanah*. You should
give him, so it has to be what you give him has
some significance. He can use it, it's a gift, you can do
something with it, okay? And therefore the minimum is enough to make
a small- the smallest of garments. לא הספיק ליתנו לו lo. עד
שצבעו *Lo hispik litno lo ad shetzeva'o*, let's say you did not
get around to giving it to him, you are processing everything, you
weren't thinking, right? So what do you do? You clean it, you
process it, then you dye it. Okay, now you don't always dye
it, but, you know, actually, I don't know, I assume even if
you- what, do people know this? Do you ever have like completely
natural wool or is it always like dyed even if
it's dyed some-? It's rare, but sometimes. Okay. So anyway, it sounds
like it was very, very regular that as a normal part of
the process, that after you cleaned it, you dyed it. So you
didn't get around to giving it to him until you got to
that stage of the process. So guess what, פטור *Patour*, you are
exempt. Why? This gets to the issue about damaging or stealing מתנות
כהונה matnos kehuna. *matnot kehunah*. If I stole something from somebody or
actually the משנה Mishnah, *mishnah* even has a case, forget that I
stole it, the idea of accidentally dyeing wool comes up in a
number of places. Michael here gives me wool to clean for him,
it's his wool, and I accidentally dye it. Is the act of
dyeing it enough of a significant change that it's essentially like I've
stolen it and taken possession and changed it and now I have
to compensate him for it, but he no longer owns it because
it's changed. Now we might not think that, we might think, you
know, color is color, maybe if I- but, you know, who knows?
You can't reverse it, he didn't- he didn't want blue wool, he
wanted red wool for all I know. So dyeing is like you
have changed it, it's like you broke it, destroyed it even if
you've made it better, but you've changed it and transformed it and
it's like it was stolen. Now we discussed before whether מתנות matanos.
כהונה *matnot kehunah* could be stolen or not, you know, which כהן
kohen *kohein* am I taking it from? But here the משנה Mishna
*mishnah* assumes that that was just when I moved it, the butcher
took it and gave it to somebody else. Did that really steal
it? It just moved it. Who was possessing it? But here we've
transformed it, then it's- you know, then it's totally a different object
and the משנה Mishna *mishnah* says it no longer belongs to the
כהנים *kohanim*. You've obviously done something wrong by transforming it but now
you have taken it out of the possession of the כהן kohen
*kohein*
and has to go again. You'd like you'd have to go find
a כהן kohen *kohein* and give it to her? Or you'd have
to find it to you? Or find- find it? No, this is
תתן titein
*titen*, this is like we said before by ראשית הגז reishis hagaze
*reishit hagez*, you have a responsibility to give it to a כהן
kohen *kohein*. Now לבנו ולא צבעו
*leibno velo tzeva'o*, if you cleansed it and did not dye it,
חייב chayav *hayav*, you're obligated, which is pretty obvious since it just
said before you have to give it to him already cleansed, already
laundered, so this isn't even a בדיעבד *bedi'avad*, this is what you
have to do. הלוקח גז gez צאנו של shel עובד oved כוכבים
kochavim, פטור מראשית הגז *Halokei'ach gez tzono shel oveid kochavim patour meireishit
hagez*. Let's say you buy the shearings of a non-Jew, the shearings
of the sheep of a non-Jew, you are exempt. Okay, that's- this,
you know. Right, צאנך, tzoncha, which is what the גמרא Gemara will
say.
So if he owned the sheep, you're exempt. הלוקח גז צאנו של
חברו, haloke'ach geiz tzono shel chaveiro,
if you purchase the shearings of your friend, so now this is
similar to buying the meat from the butcher, and so the butcher
first had the obligation but then he sold you the meat. So
here you bought the shearings,
so אם שייר המוכר חייב. im shiyer hamocher chayav. If there was
some left over in the seller's possession, then it's the seller's obligation.
So if he had a little of wool left over, that little
wool that he had left over, he has to give that to
the כהן. kohen? As opposed to the stomach and the arm and
the jaw, you don't know which part of the shearing goes to
the כהן. kohen? It's whichever part you designate. So if Michael here
had a thousand pounds of wool and he sold me nine hundred
and ninety-nine, I would say fine, but you are the one obligated,
you still have a pound left, you give to the כהן kohen.
from that remaining pound of wool. Okay. So if you had a
little bit left. לא שייר, lo shiyer, if he didn't leave anything
over, I took the whole thousand pounds, then Michael can't give anything
to the כהן kohen? anymore. Okay. And as we learned before,
it's not a monetary compensation because it's מתנות כהונה. It's about the
physical item and whose possession it is. I have all of the
wool. So in this case, הלוקח חייב, haloke'ach chayav, I would have
to give to the כהן kohen, from some of the wool. היו
לו שני מינים. hayu lo shnei minim. Let's say Michael here had
two types of wool. שחופות ולבנות, shchufos u'levanos, black wool or whatever,
gray, dirty wool, not dirty, but whatever, not black, but I don't
know, gray or whatever, some type of colored naturally colored wool, we'll
call it black, black wool and white wool. מכר לו שחופות אבל
לא לבנות. machar lo shchufos aval lo levanos. He sold me all
of his black wool, he kept all of his white wool. זכרים
אבל לא נקבות. zcharim aval lo nekeivos. He sold me all of
the wool from the males, not from the females. I guess
they produce different qualities, different types of wool. So again, Michael had
here a thousand pounds, five hundred black, five hundred white, or five
hundred from males, five hundred from females. He sold me all of
the black or he sold me all of the males. So do
I say to Michael, look, you still have five hundred pounds left,
you give the כהן kohen? everything, all of the גז, gez it's
your responsibility, you are the one that sheared it. So it says
no. The fact that they're different colors or they're from males versus
females makes them considered different shearings. And therefore, even if it's all
done at the same time, at least for the case of, maybe
not for the case where Michael had kept possession of all of
them, but at least for the case where he sold me half,
that now I have a defined segment of that wool, I have
to give to the כהן kohen from my segment, Michael gives from
his segment. Okay. זה נותן לעצמו וזה נותן לעצמו, zeh nosein l'atzmo
v'zeh nosein l'atzmo,
each one of us has to give from our segment. It's not
like Michael has something left, let him give all of it.
Let's say I'm in a שותפות, shutfos, is that considered צאני, tzoni,
or? Excellent question. The גמרא Gemara will discuss it.
The basic answer is yes, but there's actually debate
in the גמרא.
Gemara You mentioned the ראשית reishis? part of ראשית הגז. reishis ha-gez
How do you define ראשית? reishis, So, you mean, right, you mean
like, oh, you would have thought that as soon as you began
the shearing. Right. It's an interesting point. I mean,
it's sort of all done, I imagine, in one big process, but
the very first part of it. It is a good point that
the גמרא Gemara never actually, right, makes,
it's sort of like תרומה. terumah. Like תרומה terumah is called ראשית,
reishis but there's no, but you get to designate what is the
תרומה. terumah. But it's an interesting point, why it sort of learns
the concept of ראשית reishis or analogizes the concept of ראשית reishis.
to the תרומה terumah concept, which is whatever you designate, that's your
first offering, as opposed to what really was first in the process,
like by ביכורים. bikurim. Right. Okay, those are very good points, but
I would say that תרומה terumah gives, presents the opposite or a
different model for ראשית.
reshit Yes, if Michael
retained all of the different categories and they're all considered as one
wool.
Right, that is not clear from the משנה. Let's wait till we
get to the גמרא. Gemara But the משנה talks about where he
sold me one category. If he kept both, does he give two
gifts or does he give one gift? That would be the question.
So that's not in the משנה, let's bracket that till we get
to the גמרא. Gemara Okay, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara Okay,
so it says like this. במוקדשין מאי טעמא לא? b'mukdashin mai ta'ama
lo?
Why does it not apply to sanctified animals? So אמר קרא, amar
kra, the verse says צאנך, tzoncha, your sheep, the first shearings of
your sheep, ולא צאן הקדש, v'lo tzon hekdesh, so yours means also
yours, the laity, not belonging to הקדש, hekdesh, to the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash to the temple. טעמא דכתב רחמנא ta'ama d'chasav rachmana צאנך,
tzonecha, the reason is because it's written, the Torah has written צאנך,
tzonecha, your sheep. הא לאו הכי, ha lav hachi, had it not
written that, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would have thought קדשים חייבים
בראשית הגז, kodashim chayavim b'reishis hageiz, that
the sacrifices are obligated. So how could that have been, how could
I have thought that? הלא בני גיזה נינהו? hala b'nei giza ninhu?
You're not allowed to shear them. דכתיב d'chsiv ולא תגוז בכור צאנך,
v'lo sagoz bechor tzoncha,
you may not shear the firstborn of your sheep, and if that's
true about a בכור, bechor, it's true about all sacrifices. So you're
not allowed to shear it, so of course you can't be obligated
in ראשית הגז. reishis hagez Yes, Charlie? If an animal only has
monetary sanctity.
Ah, very good, next line. So the גמרא Gemara says אי בקדשי
מזבח הכי נמי, ei b'kodshei mizbe'ach hachi nami,
if it was a sacrifice... You'd be right, you're not allowed to
shear it. הכא במאי עסקינן? Hacha bimai askinan? What are we talking
about? בקדשי בדק הבית. Bekadshey bedek habayis. It's been sanctified for the
temple treasury. It's money, it's only monetarily not qua— but just for
its value. And therefore maybe you are allowed to shear it. Or
maybe the temple can shear, right? Maybe I've donated this sheep for
the temple to make money off of. Maybe they go ahead and
they shear it and they sell the shearings and it's a regular
source of income for the temple. And I want to know, right,
does the temple have to give the ראשית הגז reishis hagez to
the כהן kohen. if it's doing this shearing of these sheep in
order to make some income? So the גמרא Gemara says, והא אמר
רבי אליעזר קדשי בדק הבית אסורים בגיזה ועבודה. veha amar Rabbi Eliezer
kadshey bedek habayis asurim begiza va'avoda.
One minute, Rabbi Eliezer says that even if they're sanctified for the
temple treasury, you can't shear them and work them, which is this
strange idea because, you know, the whole point of sanctifying them is
for the temple to make money. Now of course you could make
money by going and selling them, but why shouldn't you also make
some money in terms of using them? So the גמרא Gemara says,
מדרבנן. miderabbanan. That is only rabbinic, that's not biblical. It's hard to
understand how it could be biblical. Maybe he did it because it
would be easy to confuse that with something that was sanctified as
a sacrifice, so we didn't want people to be confused. Okay, but
that's only rabbinic. Biblically you're allowed to shear it. So what if
I went ahead and I violated the rabbinic rule, I sheared these
sheep, okay, do I have to give the gift to the כהן?
kohen Whether I was the owner who sheared them before I handed
them over to the temple, or maybe the officer of the temple
sheared them and again he violated this whatever, but now we want
to know can he give, does he have to give the first
of it or part of this to the כהן? kohen. And that's
what you needed the verse. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute.
Okay wait first, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina, I would have
thought הואיל מדאורייתא בני גיזה נינהו, ho'il midoraisa benei giza ninhu, since
biblically they are fit to be shorn, היכא דגזז ליה, heicha degazaz
lei, if you did shear it and you violated the rabbinic restriction,
ליתיב ליה, liseiv lei, then you should give a portion of it
to the כהן. kohen So therefore I needed a verse to tell
me that I don't. So Chaim disagrees, is that it? If Rabbi
Eliezer says that they're אסורים מי— asurim mi— that doesn't matter. Even
Rabbi Eliezer that says that they're אסורים בגיזה ועבודה, asurim begiza va'avoda,
that's only rabbinic. So we can bracket that. So you sanctified it
for the temple, you went out and you sheared it, which biblically
minimally biblically is okay, and now we want to know do you
have to go ahead and give it to the כהן? kohen. Why
do you need my שור? shor? הקדש Hekdesh can't plow with it?
According to Rabbi Eliezer, which is I agree very strange, all they
can do is sell it, but he was maybe concerned about confusing
it for קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, one
minute, so the גמרא Gemara says, so therefore the answer is you
don't give it to a כהן, kohen. you have a פסוק. pasuk
But we're still saying why did I need a פסוק? pasuk. I
could have figured it out myself. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואקדשי,
ve'akdishei, how could I have given a portion of it to the
כהן? kohen, It's sanctified. What's a כהן kohen going to do with
sanctified wool? He has to give it to the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash anyway, it doesn't do him any good. So the גמרא Gemara
says, סלקא דעתך אמינא לפרוק וליתיב ליה. salka da'atach amina lifrok veliseiv
lei.
Maybe I would think that I now, let's say that we're not
talking about the officer of the temple, I sanctified my sheep, not
as a קרבן, korban, I sheared it.
Now I violated that rabbinic law, I sheared it. Now maybe what
I have to do is because I sheared it, I have to
give some to the כהן. kohen, You can't use it if it's
sanctified, so I would have to redeem the amount that I'm giving
to the כהן kohen, on whatever ten dollars, give that ten dollars
to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, and give that little bit of
wool to the כהן. kohen, Maybe I would have to do that
if I went ahead and I sheared it. So the גמרא Gemara
says, and therefore I needed the verse to tell me that I
don't do that.
So the גמרא Gemara says, לפרוק וליתיב ליה, lifrok veliseiv lei, the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, והא בעינן העמדה והערכה. veha ba'inan ha'amada
veha'aracha.
How can you redeem it? Don't you need to stand them up
and evaluate them? The תורה Torah says that when you sanctify an
animal, it says והעמידו הכהן והעריך אותו לפני ה׳. vehe'emido hakohen ve'erich
oso lifnei Hashem. You should stand the animal up and evaluate it
and then redeem it. Now there's a question what is that talking
about? Is it talking about sanctifying a sacrifice that got a blemish
and had to be redeemed, or is it talking even about sanctifying
an animal to the temple treasury? Now the reason that's relevant is
because the תורה Torah says you stand it up and you redeem
it, the rabbis understand that you can only redeem animals if they
are alive, if they could be stood up. If they're dead, you
can't redeem them. Okay, and the question is is that limited to
animals as sacrifices or is that even animals that were given over
to the temple treasury? Now this wool is not an animal, right?
If I sanctified my car and then it whatever dies on me,
I don't have to stand it up before I redeem it. Okay,
it's only a law about animals. But the wool was originally sanctified
as part of the sheep. So if I say that the sheep
would have to be alive and stand up to be redeemed, then
even when I shore the wool, I would not be able, is
that word shore sheared? Sheared. Even when I sheared the wool, I
would not be able to redeem it because it would not be
able to be sort of stood up. It was not it wouldn't
be alive. Okay, since it was originally sanctified as part of the
sheep. So the גמרא Gemara says how could you redeem the wool?
It's not alive and can't stand up and therefore it cannot be
redeemed. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא בעינן העמדה והערכה, veha ba'inan
ha'amada veha'aracha, it needs to be stood up to be assessed and
redeemed. הניחא למאן דאמר קדשי בדק הבית לא היו בכלל העמדה והערכה.
Ha nicha leman de'amar kadshey bedek habayis lo hayu bichlal ha'amada veha'aracha.
It works. according to one that says that things that were sanctified
for Temple treasury do not require to be stood up. That's only
a law for sacrifices. אלא ela so then fine, go ahead redeem
it, it's all only Temple sac- just- it's only for the treasury.
אלא למאן דאמר היו Ella le-man de'amar hayu according to the one
that says that even things to the Temple treasury, if they're animals,
or in this case was part of an animal, requires to be
alive and standing up, so מאי איכא למימר, mai ika le-meimar, I
couldn't have redeemed it anyway. So there's no context in which I
could have thought that I would have to give ראשית reshit הגז
to a כהן Kohen. of a sanctified animal. If it's a קרבן
korban I'm not allowed to shear it. If it's not a קרבן,
korban, then even what would I give? It would be sanctified anyway.
And you can't tell me redeem it because I wouldn't be able
to redeem it once it was shorn. So what would be the
case? So the גמרא Gemara says, so אמר רב מני בר פטיש
משום רבי ינאי, amar Rav Mani bar Patish mishum Rabbi Yannai, הכא
במקדיש בהמתו לבדק הבית חוץ מגיזותיה. hacha be-makdish behemto le-bedek ha-bayis chutz
mi-gizoseha. So what I did is I said, I am sanctifying my
sheep to the Temple treasury except for the wool. The wool I
keep possession of. So since I keep possession of the wool, then
I'm going to go ahead and shear the wool because that's why
I kept possession of it. And now that I shorn the wool,
sheared the wool, now maybe it's not sanctified, that I kept possession
of, maybe there I have to give the first of that, a
part of that shearings to the כהן. Kohen That is the question.
And therefore the verse says צאנך, tzoncha even if you kept the
wool, the sheep was owned to הקדש hekdesh and therefore you don't
have to. As long as the sheep was owned by the Temple,
even if you owned the wool, you don't have to give the
first shearings to the כהן. Kohen Okay, so that's, that was creative,
right? And now we understand why we need the פסוק. pasuk Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina,
I would have thought לגזוז, ligzoz, since he sheared it, ליתיב ליה,
leisiv lei, and now give from the shearings to the כהן, Kohen
אמר קרא, amar kra, צאנך, tzoncha even if you own the wool,
it also has to be your sheep, ולא צאן הקדש, ve-lo tzon
hekdesh, not the Temple sheep. Okay, that's great. So now the גמרא
Gemara says, נהי אי הכי, nehi ei hachi, קדשי מזבח נמי, kodshei
mizbe'ach nami, why do you have to go to a case of
Temple treasury? That's such a good answer, let's apply that even to
a sacrifice. Let's say I sanctify my sheep as a sacrifice, but
I say not the wool. Even though I'm going to offer the
sheep up as a sacrifice, well we're going to talk about if
you can do that in a minute. Okay, I'm keeping the wool
to myself. And then you could apply the same idea. So the
wool is mine, I shear it, I keep it, I don't have
to give to the כהן Kohen. because the sheep was a sacrifice.
Why did we have to run to a case of the sheep
now being owned by the Temple, by the treasury? Let it be
even a case of a sacrifice. So the גמרא Gemara says, קחשי,
kachshi, no, that you can't do because the act of shearing affects
the sheep itself, right? The sheep gets a little bit weaker in
the process of shearing. So you're actually injuring the sacrifice, you're impinging
on the actual, diminishing actual the sheep itself, and that you can't
do if it's sanctified as a sacrifice. So you wouldn't be allowed
to shear it in
that case. So the גמרא Gemara says, קדשי בדק הבית נמי קחשי,
kodshei bedek ha-bayis nami kachshi, and so what, when if let's say
it's owned by the treasury, how can you shear it if you're
actually impinging on the health of the sheep itself, which is owned
by the treasury? So the גמרא Gemara says, דאמר, de-amar, you said,
חוץ מגיזה וכחישה. chutz mi-giza ve-kechisha. You say I am sanctifying the
sheep to the Temple treasury with the ex- but what I'm keeping
to myself is the wool and any amount that it gets weakened
as a result of the shearing. That I didn't transfer over. So
don't blame me if it got a little weaker in the process
of shearing, I retained the rights to it or the ownership of
it for that amount that it would get weakened, and I'm only
giving over to the Temple the amount of what the sheep will
be the sheep post-shearing. And so there allows me to shear it,
I would think I would have to give it to the כהן,
Kohen, a part to the כהן, Kohen and the verse says no,
you don't own the sheep. You had a question? It's even more
abstract now than the כחישה. kechisha. Right, we're it's in a funny
idea because it's not like a particular physical part of it, right?
It's not like saying I own, like you could I guess imagine,
or you could imagine let's say the shearing makes the the outer
skin red and whatever and hurts just the outer skin. So maybe
you could try to focus in on a part of the sheep
and say I retain the outer layer of skin. But the גמרא
Gemara isn't doing that. The גמרא Gemara is more abstract. It's like
I'm only transferring over its value or its state post-shearing, any amount
that it diminishes in the process of shearing, I retain the rights
to that and that's under my ownership. But you're right, it is,
the גמרא Gemara deals often with this concept of owning a portion
of something. It doesn't consider it a right, it considers it a
partial ownership, but it's not divisible physically. It's more in terms of
what it functions or produces or conceptually. For example, a classic example
in the גמרא Gemara is, I own that tree for its fruit.
So you're not just selling me the fruit, it's not I have
a right to the fruit, I actually own it for its fruit.
You own it straight away, but I own it for its fruit.
So the fruit it produces is mine, but you can decide for
example to cut it down because it's your tree, but it's mine
for the fruit. So this is a type of an idea. I
own the shearing and the sheep for the amount that it gets
weaker and you own the rest. So then yes, and if he
sanctified it to the temple? Temple? So then it's going to say
do the same thing for a sacrifice then, retain that ownership for
the sacrifice.
We're about to ask that. So the גמרא Gemara says: קדשי מזבח
נמי דאמר
חוץ מגיזיה ומכחישה?
Kodshei
Mizbe'ach nami de'amar
chutz migizeha u'me'ichishah?
Say that also if it's sanctified
toward the temple, that you're retaining the shearings and the amount it
gets weaker. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אפילו הכי פשטה קדושה
בכולה. afilu hachi pashta kedusha bekulah. You can't play that game with
a sacrifice. When you sanctify part of it, the sanctity spreads throughout
the whole thing. Now, what does throughout the whole thing mean? It
could mean that, you know, the wool is always conceptually different, right?
The wool doesn't go on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. There's always an interesting
question about whether hair is considered part of the body or not.
So the wool maybe is conceptually different, and if I sanctify the
sheep maybe I can stop even as a sacrifice it spreading to
the wool. But I cannot stop it spreading to all parts of
the meat, to all parts of the actual animal itself. So I
cannot retain ownership over the weakening that's going to happen to the
sheep itself. At most I can retain ownership over the wool. So
that's what it's saying. You cannot play that game with a sanctity
of a sacrifice. By ownership you can. If all it is is
who owns it, I can split the ownership lengthwise, widthwise, any way
I want. So if I do it for the temple treasury, I
can play those games. But the idea of a sacrifice is it's
not just about, it's about sort of the identity, the function of
this. This animal is a קרבן, korban, its entire identity is to
be put up on the altar. So it's not just about ownership,
it's about its very nature. So there you cannot sort of, you
know, cut lines between the קרבן. korban. If once part of it
is identified as a קרבן, korban, that defines the whole animal. Maybe
not the wool, but certainly every part of the meat of the
animal. רש״י Rashi actually says, wait a minute, רש״י Rashi actually says
that with this answer the גמרא Gemara is even reversing itself regarding
the wool. That the גמרא Gemara is even saying that even you
can't, it's sort of going back to what it said before. You
can't even play the game with the wool. Once you sanctify for
a קרבן, korban, it defines the whole animal even the wool. But
minimally what the גמרא Gemara is saying is you certainly can't play
this game of retaining ownership of the weakening of it. That's part
of the animal itself, and no, a קרבן korban identifies the whole
animal. Let's see, feels like a מום mum or not really? No,
not a מום. mum. Well so then you just say wait till
it gets better. No, no, no, but it doesn't matter because the
whole animal is sanctified and your act of weakening it is impinging,
is hurting something that has sanctity. So it's, you know, it's a
type of מעילה. me'ilah. Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. No, not a מום, mum, but a מעילה. me'ilah. Okay, so
גמרא gemara says like this: ומנלן? u'minalan? How do you know that
you cannot sort of subdivide the קדושה kedusha of a sacrifice? דאמר
רבי יוסי, de'amar Rabbi Yose, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says, ולא במוקדשין,
va'lo bemukdashin, this is a debate in תמורה Temurah whether if I
try to say this leg is in replacement of that קרבן. korban.
So is, right, if I try to say this animal is in
replacement of this קרבן korban and it's a תמורה Temurah and both
become sanctified. But if let's say I said the leg of that
animal is in place of this קרבן, korban, does that make this
another this other animal also fully sanctified? So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says yes. And how does he say it? Because he says what
would be if you tried to sanctify just the leg? ולא במוקדשין
va'lo bemukdashin if you just tried to straight away sanctify the leg,
האומר רגלה של זו עולה כולה עולה. ha'omer raglah shel zo olah
kulah olah. If you said just the foot of this is an
עולה, olah, it would all be an עולה. olah. And therefore, so
you see within רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, and therefore if you tried
to do a תמורה Temurah to a leg, it also all becomes
a תמורה, Temurah, all becomes a sacrifice. What for us is important
is that even if I just sanctify the leg, it's not like
ownership. I can transfer ownership of the leg to the בית Beit
המקדש, HaMikdash but to identify it, to define its nature as קרבן,
korban, then if the leg is a קרבן korban the whole thing
is a קרבן. korban. And then it says, ואפילו לרבי מאיר דאמר
אין כולה עולה, va'afilu le'Rabbi Meir de'amar ein kulah olah, even רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that disagrees and says no, if you tried to
do that by the leg it would not work. הני מילי דאקדיש
דבר שאין נשמה תלויה בה. hanei milei de'akdish davor she'ein neshamah teluyah
bah. That's just because the leg, it's not it doesn't have the
soul of the animal in it. Like if you ripped off, if
you took off the leg the animal would still live. So it's
not the essence of the animal. אבל הקדיש דבר שהנשמה תלויה בה,
aval hikdish davor she'neshamah teluyah bah, let's say I sanctified the heart
of the animal or the so, you know, or the chest of
the animal or the head of the animal, then even רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir would say once that then is sort of defines the
essence of the animal. So therefore and if that is defined as
a קרבן korban then all of it is defined as a קרבן.
korban. הקדיש דבר שהנשמה תלויה בה, hikdish davor she'neshamah teluyah bah, if
you sanctified a part of the animal that the life is dependent
on, קדשה, kadsha, the entire animal is defined as a קרבן. korban.
So we are back to, so now we have saying here's why
we, here's our case about why I needed the verse to exclude,
that's what we're talking about, to exclude the shearing of a sanctified
animal. You sanctified it to the temple treasury, you retained ownership over
the wool and the weakening of the animal, you're allowed to shear
it, there you would think give from the shearings which are not
sanctified to the כהן, kohen, and it says no because the sheep
is not owned by you, it's owned by הקדש. hekdesh. Why did
we not give a similar example by a קרבן? korban? Because by
a קרבן korban you cannot divide it that way. If you sanctify
the animal, certainly you cannot retain ownership over the weakening of it,
the whole animal is a קרבן. korban. and maybe even the wool
you can't retain ownership of, but we could give that case by
the temple treasury. That's one scenario why we needed the verse to
say you're exempt. But we're not done. A couple of other scenarios.
Are you even normally allowed to do that, say I'm מקדיש makdish
it בגופיה חוץ מגיזה? b'gufeih chutz migizeh? Forget about price, yeah. Okay,
so now the גמרא gemara says, רבא Rava אמר amar במקדיש b'makdish
גזה giza עצמה, atzma, a totally different case. That was too complicated,
said רבא. Rava. Here's the case. You just sanctified not the sheep,
you sanctified the wool. Okay? Now, סלקא salka דעתך da'atach אמינא amina
נגזוז nigzoz ולפרוק v'lifrok וליתב v'leitiv ליה, lei, maybe you should shear
the wool and redeem it, give the בית המקדש HaMikdash the money
of the wool, right? Because you sanctified it, so fine transfer the
value of the wool and now give from some of the wool
to the כהן. Kohen, So אמר amar קרא kra גז gez צאנך
tzoncha. תתן titein, לו, lo. so you shall give the כהן the
shearing of your sheep. It is your sheep and the wool you've
now redeemed, so why not give it to him? Because מי mi
שאין she'ein לו מחוסר mechusar אלא גיזה giza ונתינה, un'tina, something that
all you have to do to give it to the כהן is
shear it and give it. יצא yatza זה ze שמחוסר shemechusar גיזה
giza פדייה pidya ונתינה, un'tina, it would exclude this case where you
not only have to shear it, but you also then have to
redeem it and give it. So that is where you have to
sort of re-possess it before you can give it to the כהן
is not something you're obligated. So from here, we're not excluding the
case that the בית המקדש HaMikdash owns the sheep, presumably that was
way too complicated and would not be what the משנה was talking
about, and we're talking about, and you're right, when בית המקדש HaMikdash
owns the sheep, it's obvious you're exempt. And here we're talking about
that you own the sheep, the בית המקדש owned the wool, and
I would think you would have to redeem it and the verse
of תתן titein is telling you no, since there's another step of
redeeming, then that you do not have to. But what if I
said I'm going to give a half of it to הקדש? Hekdesh?
Then I would actually have to give from my other half to
the כהן. Presumably, even though we don't know which half. Okay. אלא
צאנך tzoncha למה lamah אתא? ata? So now we are done, Bobby,
you can take a sigh of relief. We're done with the whole
issue about הקדש. Hekdesh. Now we're going to go to other issues
about what we learn from the verse. So now we're saying we
learn to exclude הקדש Hekdesh from תתן, titein we're going back to
the word צאנך. tzoncha Before we thought צאנך tzoncha, was excluding when
הקדש Hekdesh owned it, but we sort of have said that maybe
we could figure that all out ourselves. So what is צאנך tzoncha?
coming to exclude? למה lamah אתא? ata? וכדתניא, uch'detanya, and here we
go might go to your question about partnership. בהמת behemat השותפים hashutafim
חייב chayav בראשית הגז. If a non-Jew owns part of it, you're
exempt, okay, that was sort of like we know about זרוע לחיים
וקיבה, but let's say you're just partners with another Jew. Does that,
so you're obligated, why shouldn't you? רבי אלעאי Rabbi Elai, פוטר, poteir,
רבי אלעאי Rabbi Elai says no, if you're not the sole owner,
you're exempt. מאי mai טעמא ta'ama דרבי de'Rabbi אלעאי? Ilai What's the
reasoning of רבי אלעאי? Rebbi Ilai אמר amar קרא kra צאנך, tzoncha
your sheep, and it's in the singular, your singular sheep, not צאנכם,
tzonchem, your plural. So your singular means בלא belo של shel שותפות,
shutafut, only if you are the sole owner, if you are a
partner, you are exempt. ורבנן, veRabanan, what do the Rabbis do with
צאנך? tzoncha, למיעוטי l'meyutei שותפות shutafut עובד oved כוכבים, kochavim to exclude
when you're partners with a non-Jew, okay, then because a non-Jew is
exempt, your partnership with a non-Jew also exempts you. But a simple
partnership would not exempt you. ורבי veRabbi אלעאי, Ilai where does רבי
אלעאי Rebbi Ilai know that from? You first have to exclude non-Jew
before you exclude a Jew. So שותפות shutafut עובד oved כוכבים kochavim,
מנא mena ליה? lei? How does he know to exclude that case,
so then he can build on that to exclude partnership with a
Jew? נפקא nafka ליה lei מרישא mereisha דקרא, dekra, the beginning of
the פסוק pasuk. where it speaks about תרומה. Terumah. ראשית reshit דגנך,
degancha, the first of your grain, it says ראשית reshit גז צאנך
tzoncha תתן titein לו. So but it starts with the first of
your grain, תרומה. Terumah. So that singular, your grain, בלא belo של
שותפות shutafut עובד כוכבים, already excludes non-Jew. So by the time, and
it presumably that would apply to the shearings as well. So by
the time we get to the צאנך, tzoncha we've already excluded non-Jew.
צאנך tzoncha. is excluding even partnership with a Jew. ורבנן, veRabanan, what
do the Rabbis do, why don't they say the same approach as
רבי Rabbi אלעאי? Ilai? They say ראשית reshit הפסיק hifsik העניין. ha'inyan.
It says ראשית reshit דגנך degancha ראשית reshit גז צאנך tzoncha, תתן
לו. So since it says ראשית reshit, again, it could have just
said ראשית reishis דגנך degancha וצאנך vetzoncha תתן לו. Okay, so since
it wants a גז צאנך. tzoncha. Since it says the word ראשית,
reishis it's saying this is a separate subject only if you did
both you have to give it to him. Okay, so anyway, or
maybe. So anyway, they say although we've excluded partnership of a non-Jew
by תרומה, Terumah, we don't yet know what the shearing is, that's
a separate category. So therefore, when we have the word צאנך, tzoncha,
all we know to do is exclude non-Jew. We don't know that
we're building on the idea of non-Jew and can now exclude Jew.
ורבי veRabbi אלעאי, Ilai? what does רבי Rabbi אלעאי Ilai, say? ו'
vav הדר hadar ערביה, arveia, no it says וראשית v'reshit צאנך. tzoncha
So the and is connecting it, so we can apply the exclusions
by תרומה Terumah to the case of the sheep. So we know
from תרומה Terumah non-Jew is excluded, apply that to sheep, what does
וצאנך vetzoncha do according to רבי Rabbi אלעאי? Ilai It excludes even
partnership with a Jew. So the גמרא gemara's says ורבנן, veRabanan, and
the Rabbis would say back to him... If you want to say
that the תורה Torah is connecting them, why did it first use
the word ראשית reishis to separate them and then the ו vav
to reconnect them? If they really should have been connected, let it
not say the whole thing, let it just say ראשית דגנך וגז
צאנך. reishis d'gancha v'geiz tzoncha. So therefore the Rabbis insist, all right,
the Rabbis insist that they are different categories and you cannot apply
one to the other. רבי Rabbi אלעאי, Ilai? what would רבי Rabbi
אלעאי Ilai, say? אידי דהאי קדושה סתם היא והאי קדושה גוף. aidei
dehai kedusha stam hi v'hai kedusha guf. No, there's a big difference.
One is only owned by the כהן, it doesn't have any real
sanctity, as opposed to תרומה truma that has real sanctity and has
to be, you know, you can't get it טמא, tamei, you have
to eat it in certain ways and non-כהן can't eat it. So
they're big conceptual differences between them. פסק להו, pasak lehu, it wanted
to emphasize their different categories, so it had to use the word
ראשית reishis to separate them, but then it wanted to tell you
that some of the laws do apply in both cases, then הדר
ערבי להו, hadar arvi lehu, it had the ו vav to connect
them. Okay, anyway, where are we? Where we are is that everybody
agrees that תרומה, truma, if a non-Jew is a partner of yours,
is exempt. We're going to modify that in a minute. Okay, and
therefore we have the case by the sheep. So do we assume
that for sheep you have to start again from zero? And therefore
when you have צאנך, tzoncha, all it excludes is partnership of a
non-Jew? Or do we assume we already take for granted we've excluded
partnership of a non-Jew and the צאנך tsonecha. by the sheep excludes
partnership of a Jew? Okay, so that's the question. Does צאנך, tsonecha,
the ך, cha, the your, singular, exclude only partnership of a non-Jew
or even partnership of a Jew? So let's take a look. Or
excuse me, did I say that wrong? Only partnership of a non-Jew
or even partnership of a Jew. So now the גמרא gemara says
like this, ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'is eima, if you want we can say
the following. שותפות עובד כוכבים בתרומה רבנן חיובי מחייבי. shutfus akim bitruma
rabbanan chiyuvei michayvei. Let's revise this whole thing. We were assuming that
everybody agrees partnership of a non-Jew by תרומה truma is exempt. Not
so clear. Maybe the Rabbis say partnership of a non-Jew in תרומה
truma you're obligated. And we actually know that that's the case. Let's
take a look. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, ישראל
ועובד כוכבים שלקחו שדה בשותפות, Yisrael ve'akim shelachshu sade b'shutfus, a Jew
and a non-Jew own a field in partnership. They're half owners of
a field, they're joint owners, I should say. Now, and then you
go ahead and you harvest it. What is the status of the
grain? So I've now got 100 barrels or what do you have
of grain? 100, I don't know, bushels of grain. Okay, I give
50 to the non-Jew or he takes his 50, I take my
50. What do we assume? Do we assume my 50 was the
50 that grew from my portion of the field? We don't have
the field divided, you know, this, the left side is mine, the
right side is yours. My conceptual portion of the field, you know,
produced this 50 and his produced his. That's the concept of יש
ברירה, yeish breira, that how things divide up at the end, we
sort of retroactively say that's always the way they were meant to
be. So therefore since I took this 50 at the end, we'll
say this 50 grew from my portion of the field. Then it's
obligated in תרומה, truma, and the 50 that he got was from
his portion, it's not obligated. But if we say אין ברירה, ein
breira, so my both my 50 and his 50 are mixed ownership.
So this 50 bushels that I took came from the mixed ownership
of the field, so then, so then the part that's his is
exempt from תרומה, truma, the part, or מעשר, ma'aser, the part that's
mine is presumably obligated. So what, so let's take a look at
what this משנה says, ברייתא braisa says. ישראל ועובד כוכבים שלקחו שדה
בשותפות, Yisrael ve'akim shelachshu sade b'shutfus, they bought this field in partnership,
טבל וחולין מעורבין זה בזה, tevel ve'chulin me'uravin zeh b'zeh, the portion
the Jew gets and the non-Jew, but we're not we're not we're
not concerned about that, but the portion the Jew gets is a
mixture of טבל, tevel, of grain that's obligated in תרומות ומעשרות trumas
u'ma'asros and cannot be eaten without תרומות ומעשרות trumas u'ma'asros separated, and
of totally, of totally non-sanctified, non-status grain, because that's the part that's
that grew from the non-Jew's portion of the field. דברי רבי. divrei
Rebbi. That's the position of רבי. Rabbi אין ברירה, ein breira, we
don't retroactively say things worked out exactly the way they were meant
to be, okay, and therefore my portion is half is grew half
from the Jew, you know, grew from a field that was half
Jewish and half non-Jewish, and therefore it's half obligated and half not
obligated. That's what, that's what רבי Rebbi. says. רבן גמליאל אומר, Rabban
Gamliel omer, no, so ישראל חייב chayev. שלקחו shelachshu ועובד כוכבים פטור.
ve'akim patur. Everything worked out perfectly. Your portion grew from your side
of the field, his portion grew from his part of the field,
and therefore yours is totally obligated, his is totally exempt. The גמרא
gemara says, עד כאן לא פליגי אלא דמר סבר יש ברירה ומר
סבר אין ברירה. ad kan lo pligi ela d'mar savar yeish breira
u'mar savar ein breira. Here the whole debate is do we say
the concept of ברירה, breira, like is there this concept of the
way things get, you know, happen in the end, retroactively says that
they were meant to happen that way and that's the way it
was always meant to be. Okay, what? So it was באשערט. bashert.
Right, it's interesting, sometimes people say the position of ברירה breira is
a concept of, of like of, of a, what do you call
it, of, of a, not destiny, but what's the, you know, predestiny?
Yeah, like thing, yeah, but the, what's the mechanistic view of the
world in which there's the exact opposite of say, deterministic. Thank you.
It's a determinism, but it's, you know, you can go either way.
It's באשערט bashert or it's deterministic. Anyway. Anyway, okay, so, so okay,
so that's their debate. אבל שותפות עובדי כוכבים דברי הכל חייבת Aval
shutfoosto ovdei kochavim divrei hakol chayavet but notice, nobody says because a
non-Jew owns a portion, the Israel's part is exempt. It's the whole-
everybody agrees the Israel's- the Jew's part is obligated, the non-Jew's part
is exempt, and the only question is, do we each get our
own part or are they mixed together? So you see, ownership of
a non-Jew, partial ownership of a non-Jew does not exempt you. Now,
there's a huge רש"י Rashi here that tries to figure out how
do you solve the problem if it's all mixed together. Okay, and
רבי- Rebbi right, what does רבי Rebbi say? רבי, Rebbi believe it
or not, although it sounds like רבי Rebbi, is going to give
you a headache because, you know, it's all mixed together, there's no
way to solve it, רבי Rebbi actually gets you off easier because
רבי Rebbi says only 50% of the grain is obligated. So רש"י
Rashi says here's what I do. I have, like, 50 bushels, okay,
let's make it easier, I took 100 bushels, the non-Jew took 100
bushels. So I have 100 bushels, 50 of them, I don't know
which 50 of them, 50% of this is obligated, 50% is not.
So what do I do? So let's say for תרומה- trumah let's
take a מעשר, maaser, because מעשרות maasros are a tenth. So I
take 10 bushels off, and those 10 bushels I say, I say
the exact same way that the 50- the 100 bushels are totally
equally divided and you can't sub- say which is which, the same
is true about the 10 bushels that I took off. So I
say these 10 bushels are מעשר. maaser. Now, of course, only five
of them are really מעשר, maaser, but I don't know which five.
But it's okay because they're only needed מעשר maaser on 50, right?
Of the 100, only 50 is obligated. I can't just take five
because of that five only two and a half are considered to
be the, if you will, the Jewish portion. I have to take
10 so amongst the 10 I have the five that are the
Jewish portion that work against the five that are in the 100.
So in the end of the day, I'm still giving those 10
to a לוי. Levi. How is it any different than, you know,
at the bottom line than what the other opinion? I still- the
other opinion also says if I had 100, I give 10 to
the לוי. Levi. So the difference is רש"י Rashi says as follows,
is that forget these 100, I take these 100 here, now I
take some other grain that I've grown from a field that's all
mine, so that I know is 100% חייב. chayav And of that
grain that's all mine, I take five and I say this five
is going to be the מעשר maaser for these 100 bushels here.
Because of these 100 bushels, only 50 of them are obligated. So
I can take five from a different field that are definitely grown
from a Jewish field and have them redeem, you know, be the
מעשר maaser for the 100. So actually with this approach, I get
off easier, I can get off by only giving five if I
do it from another field as opposed to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel who says 100 are obligated, I would always
have to give 10. Okay, so if you want- if you're interested
in finding- reading more about that, Michael, you can read this huge
רש"י Rashi that's right to work the whole thing out. But that's
the basic- work at all because, you know, each one- right, so
רש"י Rashi deals with that, that we can consider that it remains
that way. Yeah, I think it's also you're actually sure that you're
giving the amount because even when you get 50 of the mix
or whatever, you don't really know that you got 50% in it.
Well, that's what Michael's saying, but since it's not a question of
like some grain fell in and got mixed in and then you
won't know how it got distributed, here it's really just a conceptual
distinction. It all grew, there was not a part of the land
that was mine and a part that was the non-Jew's and we
don't know whose part is whose, right? There's no- there's nothing like
we don't know certain facts. It's conceptually every single kernel is 50-50.
Okay, so therefore no matter what I take, every single kernel, every
single atom is 50-50. There's nothing that- right? So there's no like
indeterminate aspect to that. Okay, so that's how רש"י Rashi explains that
case. Now, while we're talking about it, why do we agree that-
that non-Jew's ownership of תרומה trumah is obligated, the part that's mine
is obligated, but if a non-Jew was a part owner in a
cow or in a sheep, I'm totally off the hook for תרומות
ומעשרות- trumos and maasros for- for ראשית הגז or for זרוע לחיים
וקיבה. What is the difference? So רש"י Rashi says the difference is
that a cow or a sheep is an indivisible unit. Okay, as
opposed to grain, which is always divisible. So therefore if a non-Jew
is a part owner in a field and it's an issue of
grain, then I can basically say the fact that he owns 50%
of the grain does not define the other 50% of the grain
because grain is always fundamentally divisible and doesn't sort of- it's not
like he's an owner in it as a whole, whereas if he
owns a portion of the cow or portion of the sheep, right,
then that is fundamentally one unit and therefore he is an owner
in this unit and therefore it colors and it defines the nature
of the ownership. That's the way רש"י Rashi explains it. Well, that's
true, I mean he could actually say what if he's an owner
in the leg, not just a 1% owner but an owner in
the leg of it. Okay, so that actually, you know, gets back
to the גמרא gemara before. The גמרא before actually, if you remember,
said by the case of a כהן, presumably it's the same true
of a non-Jew, only he's the part owner in the portion that-
that you're חייב in the מתנות. Okay, so anyway, that's the way
רש"י Rashi explains the difference. But now we have to Okay, well
I'm okay, so yeah, that's partly why his part is exempt, is
because his ownership of the field exempts that grain from it. But
that doesn't exempt your, but your ownership is not affected by that.
Okay, so let's keep on going. So the Baraita says like this.
So therefore, so therefore, that when it comes to trumah, everybody agrees
that his ownership does not exempt you from your part. אבל שותפות
כוכבים דברי הכל חייבת. Aval shutfut kochavim divrei hakol chayavet. But when
it comes to the ownership of a, but, of a, excuse me,
I just read the phrase. But his, so his partial ownership, his
part is exempt. But his, but his part of partial ownership does
not affect your part. Your part is still obligated. So what does
that mean? We all agree by trumah, okay, that a non-Jew is
exempt. Okay, so therefore, excuse me, a non-Jew, going too fast for
myself, I don't even know why I'm saying that. Okay, we all
agree by trumah that the non-Jewish ownership does not exempt you. So
then when we get to the shearing of the sheep, so there
the Rabbis say, "Oh, so you have צאנך. tsonecha We're not going
to jump to a Jewish partnership. We first have to establish even
non-Jewish ownership exempts because it's not the case by trumah." And רבי
אילעא Rabbi Ilai is the one that jumps all the way to
say even Jewish partnership. Okay. ואיבעית אימא תרווייהו לרבי אילעא מצאנך נפקא.
Ve-iba'it eima tarvayhu le-Rabbi Ilai mi-tsonecha nafka. Rabbi Ilai says both of
them come from the word צאנך, tsonecha meaning, before, so here we're
saying that maybe Rabbi Ilai agrees non-Jewish ownership doesn't have an impact
by trumah. But nevertheless, he's willing to learn both the exemption of
the non-Jew and of a Jew by צאנך tsonecha, by the shearings.
Why? שותפות כוכבים מאי טעמא? Shutfut kochavim mai ta'ama? What's the reason?
Once we're excluding non-Jewish ownership by the shearings, why are you exempt?
דלאו מיחד ליה? De-lav meyachad leh? Because it's not all yours. דישראל
נמי לאו מיחד ליה. De-Yisrael nami lav meyachad leh. So even if
your partner's with a Jew, it's not all yours. So basically, we're
saying, ownership of a non-Jew by trumah, that doesn't have an impact.
So we're not going to, that's not part of our conversation, because
that's actually more obligatory than the shearing. The shearing we have a
word צאנך where we're going to start excluding. So the Rabbis say
just exclude non-Jew. Rabbi Ilai says look, if we're excluding a non-Jew,
we should exclude a Jew, because the logic of excluding is that
it's not all yours. Of course, that's not necessarily the logic of
excluding. Come back, the Rabbis. For רבנן, Rabbanan, what do the Rabbis
say? עובד כוכבים לאו בר חיובא הוא ישראל בר חיובא הוא. Oved
kochavim lav bar chiyuva hu Yisrael bar chiyuva hu. No, it's not
because it's not all yours. The reason we're excluding a non-Jew is
because it's an exempt person that has a partial ownership. And therefore,
if part of it is exempt or is owned by exempt ownership,
it gets the whole sheep off. But if it's just owned by
Jewish partners and they're all obligated, there's no reason it should be
excluded. So now we have a very simple explanation of the debate.
It says צאנך, which excludes some partnership. Rabbi Ilai understands that the
point of saying yours in the possessive singular, you have to say
any partnership gets you off the hook. The Rabbis are not willing
to go that far. They'll say we're going to sort of do
the minimum that we can read in this פסוק. pasuk, Ownership by
a partner who is exempt, like a non-Jew, gets you off, but
not any partnership gets you off. Also if a partner of the
כהן, right? Because he's exempt for giving it to himself. Right, and
that's what we learned before by זרוע לחיים וקיבה, exactly. But it's
not any partnership. Now that we see that Rabbi Ilai is inclined
to say that you have to be a sole owner when the
תורה Torah uses the singular, the singular possessive, we're going to see
is this true across the board? Does Rabbi Ilai in all other
cases that the Torah speaks in singular possessive require sole ownership and
not partnership? So let's take a look. Yeah, what about community? All
right, shared ownership. All right, that's an interest word. אמר רבא מודה
רבי אילעא בתרומה. Amar Rava modeh Rabbi Ilai bi-trumah. Now we're going
to go through a whole list of things where Rabbi Ilai should
in theory demand sole ownership, but we're going to use a פסוק
pasuk to contradict it. Okay. So Rabbi Ilai agrees by trumah that
partnership does not exempt you. אף על גב דכתיב דגנך, Af al
gav de-chtiv deganecha, your grain, singular possessive, דידך ולא דשותפות, didach ve-lo
de-shutfut, only sole ownership, not partnership. כתב רחמנא תרומתיכם, Katav Rachmana trumoteichem,
your plural trumah, which makes it, once it's in the plural, it
includes even partnership. אלא דגנך למה לי? Ela deganecha lama li? Now
what do you do then with the singular possessive of your grain?
למעוטי שותפות עובד כוכבים. Le-ma'utei shutfut oved kochavim. There he agrees to
the Rabbis. Since I can't demand sole ownership completely, at least I'll
exclude ownership of a non-Jew. Of course, that's a little funny because
we just said ownership of a non-Jew doesn't exempt you by trumah.
Okay, but maybe it exempts at least his portion of it. Okay,
because as Michael said, there's even some opinions that even if a
non-Jew owns the field, the grain is obligated because the grain by
its own, having grown from a field in Israel, is obligated. So
this tells you at least his portion is exempt. When a non-Jew
owns the field, the field becomes exempt from trumah, at least his
portion becomes exempt. Okay, so that's by trumah. חלה, Challah, when it
comes to challah, אף על גב דכתיב ראשית. af al gav de-chtiv
reishit. your first. Now, that's not singular possessive, just the first. But
ואיכא למימר v'ika lemeimar נילף neilef ראשית ראשית מראשית הגז, let's connect
it to the first of the shearings, where he says it has
to be sole ownership; מה להלן דשותפות לא, mah lehalan deshutfus lo,
the same way by the shearings, not partnership, only sole ownership, אף
כאן דשותפות לא, af kan deshutfus lo, here too, not partnership, only
sole ownership. So כתב רחמנא, kasav rachmana, nevertheless the Torah writes עריסותיכם,
arisoseichem, your plural kneading troughs, so even partnership. So now the גמרא
says, I didn't need that פסוק. אלא טעמא דכתב עריסותיכם, ela taama
dechasav arisoseichem, you're telling me the only way I know partnership is
because it says your plural troughs—not troughs, what do you call it?
Trough? Kneading trough. Trough? Is it? Or is it the trough where
the sheep go and they eat and they feed from? What? That's
an אבוס. evus. That's a trough. Okay. This is a trough? I
think it was the same. Okay. Anyway, whatever. Anyway, your, okay, anyway,
הלא הכי, hala hachi, were it not that, הוה אמינא נילף ראשית
ראשית מראשית הגז. hava amina neilef reishis reishis mereishis hagez. You're saying
you needed the verse so I should not learn חלה challah from
the first shearings to say you need sole ownership. But one minute,
אדרבה, aderaba, I would never have done that. נילף מתרומה, neilef mitrumah,
let's learn out from תרומה, trumah, because we just said תרומה trumah
you don't need sole ownership. So the assumption is that if you
can learn something from one of two ways, you have חלה, challah,
do we learn from ראשית הגז that you need sole ownership to
be obligated, or do we learn from תרומה trumah that even without
sole ownership? So the general principle is, if you can be מקיש
לקולא או לחומרא, makish l'kula o l'chumra, מקיש לחומרא, makish l'chumra, we
link in the way that's more strict. But then we'd have to
say which one is more comparable though? That's true. Sometimes we use
that as a factor. The גמרא isn't getting into that, but the
גמרא's assuming that anyway we would have learned it out, you're right,
if you went by what's more comparable anyway you would have gone
by תרומה. trumah. חלה challah is much more comparable to תרומה, trumah,
right? It makes טבל, tevel, it's קודש, kodesh, and so on. So
therefore we would have learned it out from תרומה trumah and obviously
we know even partnership is obligated. So the גמרא says, you know
what, you're right. הכא נמי, hacha nami, you're right, by חלה challah
we didn't need a פסוק, we would have learned it out from
תרומה. trumah. אלא עריסותיכם למה לי? ela arisoseichem lamah li? So then
what do I do with the word your kneading whatever trough? So
what's the purpose of that word? כדי עריסותיכם kdei arisoseichem to tell
me the amount that you kneaded when you were in the wilderness.
So because there you had an עומר, omer, the גמרא figures out
how much flour comes out of an עומר omer of grain and
the מן, man, you know, was, they had an עומר לגלגלת. omer
l'gulgoles. So how much dough comes out of that? And only when
you do that amount of dough do you have to give חלה.
challah. So that's what we learn by yours, the way you did
it when you were in the wilderness, when you had this עומר
omer of the מן. man. Okay, so now what, I'm sorry it's
already 8:30, just do one more sentence. The גמרא says פאה אף
על גב דכתיב שדך, peah af al gav dichshiv sadcha, by פאה
peah although it says your field, ודאי אין ששותפות לא, vadai ein
sheshutfus lo, and I would have said only if there's sole owner,
כתב רחמנא ובקוצרכם את קציר ארצכם, kasav rachmana uv'kutzrechem es katzir artzechem,
when you cut your harvestings in the plural, so therefore even partnership.
אלא שדך למה לי? ela sadcha lamah li? So then why say
שדך sadcha in the singular? למעוטי שותפות עובד כוכבים, l'maoti shutfus oved
kochavim, if a non-Jew is a partner then you're exempt from פאה.
peah. So again, the basic thing we're going to go through is
many many times the Torah uses singular possessive. רבי Rebbi אלעאי Ilai
most of those times does not demand sole ownership because another פסוק
tells you even partnership. But then we have to say what is
the point of these words that are singular possessive? And one thing
that we can easily fall back on a lot of the time
is that at least there he'll admit that it excludes only the
idea of a non-Jew. Non-Jewish partnership will be excluded, not sole ownership.
But this is working within רבי אלעאי Ilai? that at least in
one case demands sole ownership and we are going through to see
how that does or does not play out in all these other.